<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Dissenter truely described</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36147</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1681</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32404</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12670266</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12670266</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65482</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36147)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65482)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1525:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Dissenter truely described</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for N. Thompson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:65482:1"/>
            <head>THE DISSENTER TRUELY DESCRIBED.</head>
            <l>WHat ſhall a Glorious Nation be o'rthrown,</l>
            <l>By Troops of Sneaking Raſcals of our own?</l>
            <l>Muſt Civil, and Eccleſiaſtick <hi>Laws,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Once Truckle more under the good <hi>Old Cauſe?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Shall theſe ungrateful <hi>Varlets</hi> think to Live,</l>
            <l>Only to clip Royal <hi>Prerogative?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Shall all our Blood turn Whey, whilſt we do ſee</l>
            <l>Men both Affront, and Stab the Monarchy?</l>
            <l>I'm all inflam'd with a <hi>Poetick</hi> Rage,</l>
            <l>And will Chaſtiſe the Follies of the Age.</l>
            <l>Thoughts crowd ſo faſt upon me, I muſt Write</l>
            <l>Till I've diſplay'd the Gaudy Hypocrite.</l>
            <l>He's one that ſcarcely can be call'd a Man,</l>
            <l>And yet's a Pious, Holy Chriſtian.</l>
            <l>He's big with Saving Faith (he ſays,) yet He</l>
            <l>Has not one ſpark of common Charity.</l>
            <l>'Gainſt Reaſon he perpetually Whines.</l>
            <l>Becauſe it Contradicts his Black Deſigns.</l>
            <l>He diſeſteems dull Morals; For a Saint</l>
            <l>My well beloved Brethren muſt not want.</l>
            <l>Soul-warming Thoughts; ſo warm that they did dwell,</l>
            <l>Firſt in the Womb, than at the Breaſts of Hell.</l>
            <l>He Flouts the <hi>Common Prayers,</hi> yet the poor Fool,</l>
            <l>Himſelf, not Them, does turn to Ridicule.</l>
            <l>He hates a Form, yet loves his dear Non-ſenſe;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Nauſeates</hi> his God with his <hi>Impertinence.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>With Eyes turn'd up, Mouth Screw'd, and Monkey-Face,</l>
            <l>He Lowdly Bawls to God for Saving Grace.</l>
            <l>With Meen ſo Baſe, and Scurvy, as if even</l>
            <l>His Apiſh Poſtures only would pleaſe Heaven.</l>
            <l>And then his Sniv'ling Tone, to the moſt High,</l>
            <l>He does conclude is Curious Melody.</l>
            <l>If things ſucceed not as his Humour wou'd,</l>
            <l>He ſtrait grows Angry, and he Huffs his God:</l>
            <l>And this, (as if God knew not what to do,)</l>
            <l>And that wou'd have been for thy Glory too.</l>
            <l>Then Muffled in his Cloak, <hi>Roger</hi> begins</l>
            <l>In's Sermon, to dawb forth, <hi>Soul-killing Sins;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Murder,</hi> and <hi>Theft,</hi> and <hi>Pride,</hi> and <hi>Gluttony,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            <l>Which in their <hi>Lives</hi> none more <hi>Applauds</hi> then He.</l>
            <l>Yet if you do <hi>Survey</hi> the Liſt with care,</l>
            <l>You'l quickly find <hi>Rebellion</hi> is hid there.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:65482:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l> And when he's preſt to <hi>Duties</hi> for ſome Hours;</l>
            <l>He ne'r puts in <hi>Obey the Higher Powers.</hi>
            </l>
            <lg>
               <l>At <hi>Surplice,</hi> and <hi>Lawn-Sleeves,</hi> he <hi>takes Offence,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Becauſe they are the <hi>Types</hi> of <hi>Innocence;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For that he hates, and with it men of <hi>Senſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <l>The <hi>Reverend Prelates</hi> he ſtill vilifies,</l>
            <l>'Cauſe they detect his <hi>Curſed Villanies.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Hang them, they <hi>Bark,</hi> come let us pull them down,</l>
            <l>For this ſame <hi>Mitre</hi> does <hi>Support</hi> the <hi>Crown.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>They'r the Kings <hi>Trueſt Friends,</hi> yet thought it good,</l>
            <l>To drown his <hi>Kingdoms</hi> in a <hi>Sea of Blood.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>They the Kings perſon would protect, they ſaid,</l>
            <l>Yes, yes, forſooth by <hi>Cutting off his Head;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And this they did Inſpir'd by <hi>Zeal</hi> alone,</l>
            <l>To faſten <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his <hi>Triumphant Throne.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>As if <hi>Damn'd Lyes, Falſe Oaths,</hi> and <hi>Baſe Deceit,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Propt up his <hi>Throne,</hi> and made him <hi>Truely Great.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>As if the <hi>Devil</hi> himſelf that acted them,</l>
            <l>Did bring the <hi>Luſtre</hi> to his <hi>Diadem.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Nay they go on yet with the ſame <hi>Intents,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>By molding to their Minds <hi>New Parliaments.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Some of the <hi>Great,</hi> they by their Whimſeys guide,</l>
            <l>To like their <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and to ſtem their <hi>Pride.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In other things, like methods they purſue,</l>
            <l>For even the <hi>Sh'riffs,</hi> muſt be <hi>Fanaticks</hi> too.</l>
            <l>The <hi>Judges</hi> too, they'd to their <hi>Party</hi> gain,</l>
            <l>Did they want either <hi>Honeſty,</hi> or <hi>Brain.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And when their <hi>Wheedling Tricks</hi> do fail on theſe,</l>
            <l>They poiſon ſoon ſome <hi>Country Juſtices.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Then had they once the dear <hi>Militia,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>They'd mount the <hi>Saddle,</hi> and make <hi>Charles</hi> obey:</l>
            <l>Thus firſt they'd make Him but a very <hi>Straw,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And then at <hi>Liſt Controll,</hi> and give him <hi>Law.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In fine, they are the <hi>Foes</hi> of <hi>Royal State,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Order</hi> is the great <hi>Object</hi> of their <hi>Hate.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Nor <hi>God,</hi> nor <hi>Men,</hi> theſe <hi>Furies</hi> ſeek to <hi>Pleaſe,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>They'd <hi>Bruiſe</hi> the <hi>Crown,</hi> and <hi>Tear</hi> our <hi>Surplices.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>They'd <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndermine</hi> the <hi>Churches Harmony,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And Ride a full <hi>Carier to Popery.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>They all <hi>Mankind,</hi> except Themſelves <hi>Deſpiſe,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Chiefly the <hi>Great,</hi> for being <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Wiſe.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Some <hi>Subtile</hi> have, and ſome have <hi>Giddy Souls,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Some <hi>Fools,</hi> ſome <hi>Knaves,</hi> and ſome are <hi>Knaves</hi> and <hi>Fools.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Theſe <hi>Vermine</hi> would even the beſt things <hi>Command,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And <hi>Suck</hi> up all the <hi>Sweetneſs</hi> of the <hi>Land.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>N. Thompſon, Anno Dom.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
